Guide to Esther Preston Reynolds Diaries, 1897-1923.
Fenimore Art Museum
Esther Preston Reynolds Diaries, 1897-1923.
This collection of twelve meticulously maintained diaries kept by Esther Preston Reynolds vividly portrays the lives of hard working individuals in an farm family living in the Town of Cazenovia, Madison County, NY.
1 cu. ft. (12 volumes, ca. 1,600 pages)
Reynolds, Esther Preston, 1839-1923
Fenimore Art Museum Research Library 80 Lake Road Cooperstown, NY 13326
Coll. No. 450
FM-7.2014
Acquisition Information
Coll. No. 450 is open for research according to the regulations of Fenimore Art Museum Library.
Esther Preston Reynolds, 1839-1923, was born in Madison County, NY. She graduated from Cazenovia Seminary in 1854 and in 1866 married Job. T. Reynolds, 1837-1920. They raised four children: Louisa, b. 1867; Homer, b. 1869; Lavinia, b. 1871; and Charles, b. 1872. For nearly a quarter of a century, Esther chronicled the events of her own life, her immediate family's, local inhabitants', and the surrounding area.
Biography/History
The family maintained a successful farmstead in the Town of Cazenovia, Madison County, NY. Esther managed household chores, some times assisted by her sickly daughter, Lavinia/”Vinnie,” and a neighbor lady, Mrs. Miller, whose paid labor increased as Esther became older. Her husband, successful farmer and entrepreneur Job Reynolds, managed the farm homestead, did bookkeeping for several businesses including a local cheese factory, and served in town government. Her two sons, Homer and Charles, performed a great deal of the farm labor and were musicians in a local band.
Reynolds, Job. T., 1837-1920; Reynolds, Louisa, b. 1867; Reynolds, Homer, b. 1869; Reynolds, Lavinia, b. 1871; Reynolds, Charles, b. 1872; diaries; Chittenango Falls (Madison County, N.Y.); Agricultural laborers--New York (State)--Madison County.; Families.; Farm life--New York (State)--Madison County.; Farm management--New York (State)--Madison County.; Farmers--New York (State)--Madison County.; aHops--New York (State)--Madison County.; Housewives--New York (State)--Madison County.; Madison County (N.Y.)$xSocial life and customs.; Musicians--New York (State)--Madison County.; Rural women.; Reynolds, Esther Preston, 1839-1923
This collection of twelve meticulously maintained diaries kept by Esther Preston Reynolds, 1839-1923, vividly portrays the lives of hard working individuals in an farm family living in the Town of Cazenovia, Madison County, NY).
Scope and Contents
Reynold’s entries detail the seasonal plantings and harvesting of a variety of grains, fruits, and vegetables; and carefully note the division of male and female labor and the lives of group laborers such as hop pickers and wheat thrashers.
Her entries are rich in food preparation – cooking, baking, meat brining, sausage and lard making, butter churning, and the canning of fruits – and document additional household activities such as knitting, sewing, and soap making. Trips to Cazenovia and neighboring towns to purchase textiles and household goods, visits made and received by numerous relatives and friends, social events sponsored by local churches, visits to the State Fair, and picnics sponsored by farmers’ groups are also recorded, as are library books she borrowed. Her diaries contain several pages of entries listing nearly 50 books she read. In most volumes, marriages and deaths are noted and underlined. In the back of the May 1-Dec 30, 1897 diary she made lists of Widows in Cazenovia, 1922; Births, 1901-1909; Marriages, 1897-1909; Birthdays; Deaths, 1897-1918 including details such as “killed by cars,” “drowned,” “hung himself,” and “insane.”
Her husband’s activities are also documented. In addition to managing the farm, bookkeeping, and town government work, she writes of him attending local auctions, tinkering in his farm workshop, and making and repairing farm tools and implements such as “whiffletrees.”
Reynold's entries concerning the lives of her two sons, Homer and Charles, are especially detailed. They did a great deal of the farm labor including haying, hauling produce and grains to grist mill or market, repairing outbuildings, and managing livestock. Mother Esther also recorded their band performances for a variety of local and farther-flung “entertainments,” their many travels, socializing, loves and subsequent marriages, births and child rearing experiences.
- 450.v1 Diary, May, 1897 - December, 1897
- 450.v2 Diary, January 1, 1898 - August 14, 1899
- 450.v3 Diary, August 15, 1899 - December 22, 1900
- 450.v4 Diary, December 23, 1900 - July 11, 1902
- 450.v5 Diary, July 12, 1902 - December 31, 1903
- 450.v6 Diary, January 1, 1904 - May 7, 1906
- 450.v7 Diary, May 9, 1906 - December 31, 1908
- 450.v8 Diary, January 1, 1909 - October 31, 1912
- 450.v9 Diary, November 1, 1912 - November 19, 1917
- 450.v10 Diary [12/04/17 "The President sails today to make peace"], November 20, 1917 - December 31, 1918
- 450.v11 Diary [double entries for 1919 and 1920, 1921], January 1, 1919 - January 21, 1921
- 450.v112 Diary [last entries short and in shakey hand, about weather and visitors], January 1, 1921 - December 4, 1923